<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Topher Chapman</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.topherchapman.com/feeds/advice.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2017-07-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated><entry><title>Do Authors Deserve to be Paid?</title><link href="/blog/2017/Jul/03/do-authors-deserve-to-be-paid/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2017-07-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Topher Chapman</name></author><id>tag:,2017-07-03:blog/2017/Jul/03/do-authors-deserve-to-be-paid/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’m not gonna bury the lede, folks.  Because there’s no tiptoeing my way into this controversy.  The answer is&amp;nbsp;“No.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“Hell no”,&amp;nbsp;even.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Authors do not &lt;em&gt;deserve&lt;/em&gt; to be&amp;nbsp;paid.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Boy, I can already smell the smoke.  The comments on this are going to be &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FIRE&lt;/span&gt;!  I’m going to need a minute to put on this flame-retardant&amp;nbsp;suit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[insert sounds of me grunting my way into scratchy, asbestos pants over&amp;nbsp;here]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay.  I’m ready&amp;nbsp;now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s&amp;nbsp;talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like I was saying, authors don’t deserve any money.  But, should they &lt;em&gt;earn&lt;/em&gt; it?  Of course!  Therein lies the rub, right?  The difference between “deserve” and&amp;nbsp;“earn”.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mean, what if I think your writing is &amp;#8230; uh &amp;#8230; we’ll just say “not my thing.”  Even if I acquired it though non-compensatory means (i.e. *hand over my eye and a sneer* Pirated!), it’s still going to be a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DNF&lt;/span&gt;, and is eventually getting deleted to make room for more cat&amp;nbsp;photos.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An even worse case?  I paid you money and &lt;em&gt;then&lt;/em&gt; hated your&amp;nbsp;book.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“But, you paid for the book instead of stealing it from me!  How is that worst&amp;nbsp;case?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whoa, whoa, whoa.  Slow down there,&amp;nbsp;turbo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, yes, I paid for your book, but I promise you’d rather I didn’t.  In fact, let’s look at our possible&amp;nbsp;outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outcome One:&lt;/strong&gt; I buy your book, read the first couple chapters, and hate it.  I feel slighted since I paid good money for something that was wholly dissatisfying.  I feel robbed.  I immediately go to every ratings site everywhere and 1-Star the thing into oblivion.  I tell all my friends how I felt ripped off by your awful prose and unfulfilled promises.  My facebook.  My twitter.  My entire social graph — most of whom have similar tastes and preferences as I do — now spread that opinion among &lt;em&gt;their&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Everyone(!) needs to know how you took my money and gave me misery in&amp;nbsp;return.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure, you gained a sale, but it potentially cost you dozens more.  &lt;a href="http://tvtropes.org/pmwiki/pmwiki.php/Main/ThePointsMeanNothing"&gt;Sales score:  &lt;em&gt;-300 Reputation&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outcome Two:&lt;/strong&gt; I find your book laying around in cyberspace (“Oh!  Lookie here!  What’s that doing just laying around?”), read the first couple chapters, and hate it.  I click delete, immediately forget your name, and go back to surfing &lt;a href="http://www.lolcats.com/"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;LOL&lt;/span&gt; Cats&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You didn’t gain a sale, but since you didn’t offend me, you didn’t lose anything either.  Sales score:  &lt;em&gt;Plus Nothing&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obviously, &lt;em&gt;Outcome One&lt;/em&gt; is pretty extreme, but option two is pretty average.  People who wouldn’t normally give you money aren’t giving you money because they’re not interested in what you, as an author, have to&amp;nbsp;offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You didn’t earn their money, so you don’t &lt;em&gt;deserve&lt;/em&gt; their&amp;nbsp;money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="You’re entitled to NOTHING" src="/support/images/entitled.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“But they read&amp;nbsp;it!”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Probably not.  Maybe parts of it.  Even the most die-hard, [insert soup-nazi-like-writer-stereotype here] author can&amp;#8217;t look at a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DNF&lt;/span&gt; and honestly say, “That was a&amp;nbsp;success!”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s crazy&amp;nbsp;talk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not like we authors are selling steak and potatoes here.  It’s not like the reader ate everything but the carrots in the side salad, and demanded a refund because it tasted funny.  In that case, they still got to eat.  Their belly is still&amp;nbsp;full.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the situation where a reader buys your book, and only reads two-thirds of it, you’re like a sticky, grubby taxi that runs out of gas.  While stuck in traffic.  Miles away from the destination.  And still makes you pay full-fare as if they&amp;#8217;d dropped you off at your&amp;nbsp;doorstep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You cost them time they’re never getting back.  You cost them money.  And they’re not anywhere near where they wanted to be taken when they first initiated the experience with&amp;nbsp;you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not only did you not &lt;em&gt;earn&lt;/em&gt; the money they already gave you, but you might have irritated them instead!  The only thing you&amp;#8217;re earning from them (not to mention anyone they talk to) are eyerolls and mutterings of, &amp;#8220;that book&amp;nbsp;sucks.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, my point is that terrible experiences happen.  People buy books all the time they don’t finish because it wasn&amp;#8217;t worth finishing.  In those cases, the authors didn’t &lt;em&gt;earn&lt;/em&gt; that money, yet they still took&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you think about it, it&amp;#8217;s kind of a terrible system we&amp;#8217;ve set up.  And it&amp;#8217;s rigged against the&amp;nbsp;reader.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s because, unlike a perfectly cooked, medium-rare steak, or the shoes on your feet, or that new bottle of body wash in your bathtub, storytelling is a service — not a product.  (btw, you should really frost the glass in your bathroom window.&amp;nbsp;*wink*)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I mean, you don&amp;#8217;t want to be &lt;em&gt;that guy&lt;/em&gt; who delivers a swift kick to someone&amp;#8217;s dark parts only to turn around and &lt;em&gt;demand&lt;/em&gt; payment because they already consumed your &amp;#8220;product&amp;#8221;,&amp;nbsp;right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Right?!?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Disappointed panda is disappointed" src="/support/images/disappointed-panda.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“But how will I make money as an&amp;nbsp;author?!?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hate to be the one to break this to you, but maybe you&amp;nbsp;don’t.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe you’re not good enough and people don’t want to pay you for your stories yet.  Maybe you need more practice at the craft.  In this world of instant-expert gratification and self-talent overestimation, maybe you haven’t put in enough&amp;nbsp;work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Newsflash:  Crafting compelling stories is pretty flipping&amp;nbsp;hard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, let’s agree to not conflate creating low quality stories no one wants to read with people &amp;#8220;stealing&amp;#8221; your work by not paying&amp;nbsp;you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, and can we talk about that for just a&amp;nbsp;second?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Huh?&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s not actually stealing, you know.  If I have &lt;em&gt;a copy&lt;/em&gt; of your text, digitally, on my computer, that doesn’t remove it from yours.  I didn’t &lt;em&gt;steal&lt;/em&gt; it.  You still have your&amp;nbsp;original.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s actually&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8230; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You know&amp;nbsp;what?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On second thought, you don’t want to get me ranting on that right now.  This post is running long as it is.  So, let’s put a pin in it, shall we?  We’ll crack that piracy-is-not-theft nut sometime&amp;nbsp;later.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where was&amp;nbsp;I?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“People shouldn’t give me money for my hard work&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8230;”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oh, yeah!  That’s&amp;nbsp;right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That’s a great point — Authors should give their work away for&amp;nbsp;free!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*goes in for a&amp;nbsp;high-five*&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Um, &lt;em&gt;hello?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Are you still there?  What are you doing on the floor?  That looks &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;uncomfortable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, it should be baked into your sales strategy as an author to give your work away.  It’s a great, low-friction way for readers to discover your&amp;nbsp;words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“But, how am I supposed to make money if I’m giving away the results of my sweat and effort for&amp;nbsp;free?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good question.  A bit gross, but&amp;nbsp;good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Couple things&amp;nbsp;here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1) You’re not going to have a career in writing if you’re a “one and done” author, right?  I mean, you’re a writer, so you write.  It’s what you do.  That means, you don’t have to give away &lt;em&gt;everything&lt;/em&gt;, just your very best stuff in order to build a&amp;nbsp;fanbase.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2) It’s not a binary thing — You don’t &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EITHER&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; give away your work &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;OR&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; charge for it.  You can do &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BOTH&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.  For example, you can host your work for free on your website while still having a kindle version on Amazon and a paper version in&amp;nbsp;stores.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“That&amp;#8217;s insane.  Why would anyone pay for my book if I’m giving it away for&amp;nbsp;free?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Again, great question.  You’re good at&amp;nbsp;this!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One way is to think of ebooks as marketing for your glossy, lavishly delicious hardbacks.  Or, think of ebooks as a super-low-friction-one-click way for people to get their hands on your books.  (unlike pirated ebooks.  there&amp;#8217;s nothing low friction about&amp;nbsp;them)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;#8217;s just the beginning.  Let&amp;#8217;s look at a fistful of&amp;nbsp;examples!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years ago Neil Gaiman &lt;a href="http://journal.neilgaiman.com/2008/02/kids-free-book.html"&gt;gave away &lt;em&gt;American Gods&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for free on his website.  Harper Collins was &lt;a href="http://journal.neilgaiman.com/2008/07/results-of-free.html"&gt;terrified&lt;/a&gt; it was going to destroy sales of the book.  &lt;a href="http://www.cleveland.com/books/index.ssf/2011/06/in_one_decade_neil_gaimans_ame.html"&gt;It didn’t&lt;/a&gt;.  And, I guess we all know &lt;a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt1898069/"&gt;what happens next&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;“But, he’s super-famous.  That won’t work for&amp;nbsp;me.”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What about &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2007/sep/18/informationeconomy"&gt;Cory Doctorow&lt;/a&gt; then?  He&amp;#8217;s given away &lt;a href="https://mises.org/blog/cory-doctorow-giving-away-free-e-books-and-morality-%E2%80%9Ccopying%E2%80%9D"&gt;every single book he&amp;#8217;s ever written for free&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Yeah, well, sure he&amp;#8217;s not as famous, but he&amp;#8217;s got a schtick.  He&amp;#8217;s an&amp;nbsp;activist.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maybe &lt;a href="http://www.hughhowey.com/me-and-the-pirates-are-tight/"&gt;Hugh Howey&lt;/a&gt; is closer to your situtation?  He&amp;#8217;s not super-famous or a heavy activist, but is still crushing it with that &amp;#8220;giving his work away&amp;#8221;&amp;nbsp;thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;But &amp;#8230;&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8220;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or maybe you&amp;#8217;re more of a &lt;a href="https://www.wattpad.com/story/7835597-oryx-and-crake-maddaddam-trilogy-1"&gt;Margaret Atwood&lt;/a&gt; fan?  She&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt5834204/"&gt;kind of poignant&lt;/a&gt; right now.  And, of course, is giving her work away for&amp;nbsp;free.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Well &amp;#8230;&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8220;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ooooh!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have an idea!  A&amp;nbsp;side-quest!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wander over to Amazon&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/Best-Sellers-Kindle-Store/zgbs/digital-text/ref=zg_bs?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;tf=1"&gt;Top 100 Free Ebooks&lt;/a&gt; list and grab a few of the authors you see there.  Any of them, really.  Then, go to their &lt;a href="https://www.amazon.com/K.N.-Lee/e/B00CR5IPGM/ref=zg_bs_digital-text_f_bl_18?_encoding=UTF8&amp;amp;refRID=YJXGT85J2FJ85E02AARC"&gt;Author Page&lt;/a&gt;, scroll down, and check out their &amp;#8220;Amazon Author Rank&amp;#8221; for &lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;paid sales&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These folks are &lt;em&gt;filled with win&lt;/em&gt; and real-life &lt;em&gt;revenue&lt;/em&gt; because they give away their books.  It&amp;#8217;s like they say, &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.techdirt.com/articles/20070215/002923/saying-you-cant-compete-with-free-is-saying-you-cant-compete-period.shtml"&gt;if you can&amp;#8217;t compete with free, you can&amp;#8217;t compete&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;.  (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AKA&lt;/span&gt;, the &amp;#8220;selling a bottle of basically-free-water for two bucks&amp;#8221;&amp;nbsp;thing)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This works because &lt;em&gt;your primary focus should be fighting obscurity&lt;/em&gt;, not demanding money you don&amp;#8217;t deserve because you haven&amp;#8217;t earned it&amp;nbsp;yet.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Obscurity is your enemy, folks.  Not&amp;nbsp;pirates.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;So I should just ignore people stealing my&amp;nbsp;work?&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dude.  Not&amp;nbsp;stealing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Whatever.  You&amp;#8217;re saying I should ignore&amp;nbsp;pirates?&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Absolutely!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They&amp;#8217;re not gonna give you money anyway.  And, a bit of free advice:  You can&amp;#8217;t stop them.  A nerd with a library card and a &lt;a href="https://github.com/tesseract-ocr/tesseract"&gt;github account&lt;/a&gt; is all it takes.  Every book ever printed can be obtained for free if you hang out in the right &lt;a href="https://irc-source.com/channel/UnderNet/%23bookz"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;IRC&lt;/span&gt; channels&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It&amp;#8217;s out of your&amp;nbsp;control.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="Ignored pirate is ignored" src="/support/images/call-me-matey.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead, focus on what you &lt;em&gt;can&lt;/em&gt; control.  Find your &lt;a href="http://kk.org/thetechnium/1000-true-fans/"&gt;1000 true fans&lt;/a&gt;.  Once you shed that lingering terror from giving your work away, you can &lt;em&gt;proactively&lt;/em&gt; use &lt;a href="http://www.justwriteabook.com/blog/book-promotion/ebook-publishing-profits-5-front-and-backmatter-tips/"&gt;lots of strategies&lt;/a&gt; in your ebooks to leverage these sharing networks so they can help you find your true&amp;nbsp;fans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because, if your books are basically marketing materials &lt;em&gt;with or without&lt;/em&gt; your permission, you may as well take advantage of&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, ask them for favors in your ebook&amp;#8217;s front matter.  Ask the people sharing your work around for a few&amp;nbsp;things:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Rate your book &lt;em&gt;favorably&lt;/em&gt; (since you&amp;#8217;re nice enough to share your work with them &amp;#8212; reciprocity &lt;em&gt;works&lt;/em&gt;, friends) on Goodreads and&amp;nbsp;Amazon  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Tell everyone they know about&amp;nbsp;it  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Send you&amp;nbsp;money!  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That last bullet is the complicated one.  It can be remarkably hard to compensate authors.  It probably warrants a post all itself talking about how author donations intersect with a publisher&amp;#8217;s sales&amp;nbsp;expectations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Regardless, all authors should be taking advantage of as many revenue streams as&amp;nbsp;possible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Revenue streams&amp;nbsp;like:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href="https://cash.me/$m3mnoch"&gt;Square Cash&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href="http://fantasy-faction.com/support-us"&gt;Paypal link on your&amp;nbsp;site&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.patreon.com/FantasyFaction"&gt;Patreon account&lt;/a&gt; for&amp;nbsp;subscriptions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;And, of course, standard book&amp;nbsp;sales&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give you hope (or maybe just depress you more), think about this:  There are &lt;em&gt;three billion people&lt;/em&gt; on the internet.  Without getting into weird math probabilities using non-negative matrix factorization, I&amp;#8217;m going to point out if you could reach 0.0005% of those people?  And talk them into giving you just one dollar a month?  Well, you&amp;#8217;d have yourself a tidy $180,000-per-year writing&amp;nbsp;career.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like everyone says, though:  &lt;em&gt;Money shouldn’t be your first&amp;nbsp;goal.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before anything else, you need to love to write.  You need to prove you can write.  That you can tell a compelling story.  Then, eventually, you won’t have gotten any money you deserve, you’ll instead have received all the money you’ve &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EARNED&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But, step one of transitioning to a paid writing career is finding your fans, man.  Everything else&amp;nbsp;follows.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Canceling EA Access from Xbox</title><link href="/blog/2015/Nov/14/canceling-ea-access-xbox/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2015-11-14T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Topher Chapman</name></author><id>tag:,2015-11-14:blog/2015/Nov/14/canceling-ea-access-xbox/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;good lord.  that took forever to&amp;nbsp;find.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for those of you looking:  “how do i cancel my ea access subscription?”  it’s actually from microsoft and not ea.&amp;nbsp;duh…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;step one:&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href="https://account.microsoft.com/services"&gt;https://account.microsoft.com/services&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;step two:&lt;/em&gt;  click cancel on the ea access&amp;nbsp;one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;super easy once you know where the hell to&amp;nbsp;look.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Today’s Economic Thought</title><link href="/blog/2011/May/25/todays-economic-thought/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-05-25T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Topher Chapman</name></author><id>tag:,2011-05-25:blog/2011/May/25/todays-economic-thought/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;here’s the thought that just occurred to&amp;nbsp;me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;technology greatly increases the commoditization of goods and&amp;nbsp;services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;thanks to &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gossen%27s_laws"&gt;gossen’s laws&lt;/a&gt;, we know that as commodity consumption rises, marginal utility eventually falls to zero and reaches maximum total&amp;nbsp;utility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if total utility is zero (or even close to zero) amongst all things, there is no differentiation between similar goods and&amp;nbsp;services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;with no differentiation and the ability to consume goods and services ulitmately limited by time (the one, true finite resource), demand is also&amp;nbsp;finite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;supply-side economics is broken because it relies on temporary increases in total utility when total utility is already&amp;nbsp;maximized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;whew…  that’s about all the economic brain cells i have right now.  tho, feel free to point out weird missing strawman&amp;nbsp;holes.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Answering Questions About Solar Panels for Your Home</title><link href="/blog/2011/May/10/solar-questions/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-05-10T00:00:00-07:00</updated><author><name>Topher Chapman</name></author><id>tag:,2011-05-10:blog/2011/May/10/solar-questions/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;going in, we had (and met) three&amp;nbsp;goals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;No added expense&lt;/em&gt; - we didn’t want to be saddled with any extra payments and we assuredly didn’t want to trade liquid cash for a non-liquid asset. there was no way we wanted to wait forever for our investment to recoup. to avoid that, we calculated how many solar panels we’d need to leave our total monthly energy payment unchanged. so, the total of our loan payment added to the new power bill ($10 to $30 a month, depending) is less than or equal to our old power&amp;nbsp;bill.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;adding equity to our home&lt;/em&gt; - talk about instant equity!  &amp;#8220;here person buying our house, i hope you like your $15 a month electric bill!“  over the course of 30 years, that’s $54,000 in savings if energy prices stay the&amp;nbsp;same.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;saving money long term&lt;/em&gt; - speaking of energy prices staying the same. did you know that power rates in 1990 out here were 9.9 cents per kilowatt hour? now, they’re 15.38 cents. yeah… that’s a 50% increase. and next year, they’re going up to 15.57 and the year after that, the power company is saying they’re going to be 15.61. for those keeping track at home, that’s about a 2% increase per year. not for&amp;nbsp;us!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;you’ll notice i didn’t say &amp;#8220;being green”, tho, that’s a nice side effect, it certainly wasn’t the driving reason. it’s funny how many people think we did it because we’re crazy californian hippies. makes me laugh. no, it has nothing to do with that at all. i mean, have you looked at your power bill&amp;nbsp;lately?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;joc did tons and tons of research prior to the install and we ended up choosing marie phillip at herca solar here in san diego (&lt;a href="http://www.hercasolar.com"&gt;http://www.hercasolar.com&lt;/a&gt;) – they were awesome and are highly recommended by us to anyone interested. just tell them joc and i sent&amp;nbsp;you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;so, to recap: our monthly power budget at worst (until the loan is paid off) is a little less than before the panels, we added a ton of equity to the house and we’ve insulated ourselves from future power rate increases. win, win and&amp;nbsp;win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;hell, all we need now is an electric car and we’ll be the hippies with the $15 power bill to your $200 one and our $0.00 a month fuel bill to your $200 one.
tho, i suppose at least you won’t be called a&amp;nbsp;hippy.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>