<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Topher Chapman</title><link>/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://www.topherchapman.com/feeds/rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Mon, 29 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0800</lastBuildDate><item><title>FanFic Fight Scene</title><link>/blog/2016/Feb/29/fanfic-fight-ff/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;sort of like the summary above alludes to, i relished this opportunity to address a terrible grievance cast upon the world.  this one, right&amp;nbsp;here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PsZ-acZYqco&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in the first 30 seconds of that video, something so very wrong gets spoken, that it made me literally cry out and stomp my feet in&amp;nbsp;outrage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;there is no goddamn way drogo would beat conan in a&amp;nbsp;fight.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;take, for example, the most relevant detail:  drogo lives in a gritty, realistic world.  conan lives in over-the-top crazy town.  ffs, conan snapped the neck of a bull when he was a teenager!  with his bare&amp;nbsp;hands!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(note, i&amp;#8217;m talking about &lt;em&gt;literary&lt;/em&gt; conan here, not &lt;em&gt;ah-nahld&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;conan)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it&amp;#8217;s like saying, who would win in a fight &amp;#8212; wolverine or mike tyson in his prime?&amp;nbsp;duh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;anyway, &lt;a href="http://fantasy-faction.com/forum/(feb-2016)-fanfic/(feb-2016)-fanfic-submission-thread/msg134396/#msg134396"&gt;my entry&lt;/a&gt; this month explores the&amp;nbsp;topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i&amp;#8217;ve recreated it here, for your fancy reading:  &lt;a href="/stories/bulls-and-horses"&gt;Bulls and&amp;nbsp;Horses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Topher Chapman</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 29 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>tag:,2016-02-29:blog/2016/Feb/29/fanfic-fight-ff/</guid></item><item><title>Even More Clarion</title><link>/blog/2016/Feb/16/second-clarion-story/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;here we go again!  the second of my entries to that fancy &lt;a href="http://clarion.ucsd.edu/index.html"&gt;clarion workshop&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;this time, it&amp;#8217;s a short story about some poor woman, broken and suffering after crashing to the ground &amp;#8212; if only she&amp;#8217;d not botched the assassination&amp;nbsp;attempt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/stories/stress-fracture"&gt;Stress Fracture&amp;nbsp;Excerpt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Topher Chapman</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 16 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>tag:,2016-02-16:blog/2016/Feb/16/second-clarion-story/</guid></item><item><title>Applying to Clarion</title><link>/blog/2016/Feb/09/clarion-application/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;wait &amp;#8212; what is clarion, you ask?  here&amp;#8217;s what they&amp;nbsp;say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clarion is an intensive six-week summer program focused on fundamentals particular to the writing of science fiction and fantasy short stories. It is considered a premier proving and training ground for aspiring writers of science fiction, fantasy, and horror. Instructors are among the most respected writers and editors working in the field today. Over one third of our graduates have been published and many have gone on to critical acclaim. The list of distinguished Clarion alumni includes Ed Bryant, Octavia Butler, Bob Crais, Cory Doctorow, George Alec Effinger, Nalo Hopkinson, James Patrick Kelly, Vonda McIntyre, Kim Stanley Robinson, Martha Soukup, Kelly Link, Bruce Sterling, and many&amp;nbsp;others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;apparently, they only take 18 people each year.  well, here goes&amp;nbsp;nothing&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i&amp;#8217;m working through two of my short stories right now for submission.  in theory, they&amp;#8217;re supposed to represent my best work to&amp;nbsp;date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;you tell me if you think it&amp;nbsp;is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;here&amp;#8217;s the opening scene for a story about guns and dragons (it&amp;#8217;s like peanut butter and chocolate!):  &lt;a href="/stories/hearts-of-fire"&gt;Hearts of Fire&amp;nbsp;Excerpt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Topher Chapman</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2016 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>tag:,2016-02-09:blog/2016/Feb/09/clarion-application/</guid></item><item><title>Breaking the Fourth Wall</title><link>/blog/2016/Jan/14/fourth-wall-ff/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;so it turns out this month&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://fantasy-faction.com/forum/(jan-2016)-breaking-the-fourth-wall/(jan-2016)-breaking-the-fourth-wall-submission-thread/msg128612/#msg128612"&gt;fantasy faction contest&lt;/a&gt; was to write a story about breaking the fourth wall.  &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourth_wall"&gt;wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; has a pretty good description of just what that means if you&amp;#8217;re&amp;nbsp;not familiar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;long story short (ha!  see what i did there?!?), it&amp;#8217;s a device that works well&amp;nbsp;with comedy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i can totes&amp;nbsp;do funny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;so, yeah, this month was fun to write.  originally, i was planning on doing a zombie hunter thing &amp;#8212; had a great nugget of an idea that i may revive (see?  funny!) later.  that&amp;#8217;s when i remembered a conversation my d&amp;amp;d guys and i had ages ago.  it involved dragons, so, of course, i wrote about dragons.
finally, here it is:  &lt;a href="/stories/fucking-dragon"&gt;But, I’m a&amp;nbsp;F#@%ing Dragon!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Topher Chapman</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2016 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>tag:,2016-01-14:blog/2016/Jan/14/fourth-wall-ff/</guid></item><item><title>Oooh, Look! YACB!</title><link>/blog/2015/Dec/28/blog-announcement/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;it seems like at least once a year, i fire up a new blog.  since it&amp;#8217;s usually just for the sake of trying out a new blogging platform, most of them don&amp;#8217;t even get past &lt;a href="http://addictingentertainment.com"&gt;the first post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;however, this one is different!  i actually have a legitimate reason to blog&amp;nbsp;now!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;lookit me!  i&amp;#8217;m a&amp;nbsp;writer!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;at least, i&amp;#8217;m doing it as a easy-to-put-down-and-pick-back-up outlet for this &lt;em&gt;wellspring&lt;/em&gt; of creativity i have going.  and i&amp;#8217;ve always enjoyed writing, so getting deeper into the craft is&amp;nbsp;cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;what kind of stuff am i going to&amp;nbsp;write?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;nice of you to ask!  basically, i&amp;#8217;m a genre writer &amp;#8212; mostly fantasy.  maybe a little sci-fi.  maybe a little horror.  hell, i may even get into that weird urban&amp;nbsp;stuff.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;/fistpump&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;what&amp;#8217;s with the weird domain?  topher chapman?&amp;nbsp;what?!&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;so, now that i&amp;#8217;m well on my way to becoming one of those super-famous writers, i was thinking it was time to stake out a mostly recognizable and sorta-kinda unique pen&amp;nbsp;name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it came down to a choice between &amp;#8220;topher chapman&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;astropants starshine&amp;#8221; &amp;#8212; so you can tell which side of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;THAT&lt;/span&gt; fence i came down&amp;nbsp;on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;what are all these old&amp;nbsp;posts?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;since i&amp;#8217;ve got lots of random writing laying around all over the place from some 20 years of blogging, (i started back when they were called &amp;#8220;online diaries&amp;#8221; and they had a &amp;#8216;~&amp;#8217; in the &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/*/http://mediaphex.com/~chris"&gt;url mapping&lt;/a&gt; to my home directory &amp;#8212; ahhhh&amp;#8230;  the &lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20000817183454/http://www.m3mnoch.com/"&gt;good ol&amp;#8217; days&lt;/a&gt;) i figured i&amp;#8217;d reach out and grab a few of the more pertinent, and less aggro-inducing posts and copy them over&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;or maybe just any old thing that seems&amp;nbsp;interesting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;anyway, &lt;a href="mailto:chris@topherchapman.com"&gt;drop me a line&lt;/a&gt; if you have any comments or such.  i&amp;#8217;d love to hear&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Topher Chapman</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 28 Dec 2015 14:05:12 -0800</pubDate><guid>tag:,2015-12-28:blog/2015/Dec/28/blog-announcement/</guid></item><item><title>Canceling EA Access from Xbox</title><link>/blog/2015/Nov/14/canceling-ea-access-xbox/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;good lord.  that took forever to&amp;nbsp;find.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for those of you looking:  “how do i cancel my ea access subscription?”  it’s actually from microsoft and not ea.&amp;nbsp;duh…&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;step one:&lt;/em&gt;  &lt;a href="https://account.microsoft.com/services"&gt;https://account.microsoft.com/services&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;step two:&lt;/em&gt;  click cancel on the ea access&amp;nbsp;one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;super easy once you know where the hell to&amp;nbsp;look.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Topher Chapman</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2015 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>tag:,2015-11-14:blog/2015/Nov/14/canceling-ea-access-xbox/</guid></item><item><title>Today’s Economic Thought</title><link>/blog/2011/May/25/todays-economic-thought/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;here’s the thought that just occurred to&amp;nbsp;me:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;technology greatly increases the commoditization of goods and&amp;nbsp;services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;thanks to &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gossen%27s_laws"&gt;gossen’s laws&lt;/a&gt;, we know that as commodity consumption rises, marginal utility eventually falls to zero and reaches maximum total&amp;nbsp;utility.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if total utility is zero (or even close to zero) amongst all things, there is no differentiation between similar goods and&amp;nbsp;services.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;with no differentiation and the ability to consume goods and services ulitmately limited by time (the one, true finite resource), demand is also&amp;nbsp;finite.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;supply-side economics is broken because it relies on temporary increases in total utility when total utility is already&amp;nbsp;maximized.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;whew…  that’s about all the economic brain cells i have right now.  tho, feel free to point out weird missing strawman&amp;nbsp;holes.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Topher Chapman</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 25 May 2011 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>tag:,2011-05-25:blog/2011/May/25/todays-economic-thought/</guid></item><item><title>Answering Questions About Solar Panels for Your Home</title><link>/blog/2011/May/10/solar-questions/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;going in, we had (and met) three&amp;nbsp;goals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;No added expense&lt;/em&gt; - we didn’t want to be saddled with any extra payments and we assuredly didn’t want to trade liquid cash for a non-liquid asset. there was no way we wanted to wait forever for our investment to recoup. to avoid that, we calculated how many solar panels we’d need to leave our total monthly energy payment unchanged. so, the total of our loan payment added to the new power bill ($10 to $30 a month, depending) is less than or equal to our old power&amp;nbsp;bill.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;adding equity to our home&lt;/em&gt; - talk about instant equity!  &amp;#8220;here person buying our house, i hope you like your $15 a month electric bill!“  over the course of 30 years, that’s $54,000 in savings if energy prices stay the&amp;nbsp;same.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;saving money long term&lt;/em&gt; - speaking of energy prices staying the same. did you know that power rates in 1990 out here were 9.9 cents per kilowatt hour? now, they’re 15.38 cents. yeah… that’s a 50% increase. and next year, they’re going up to 15.57 and the year after that, the power company is saying they’re going to be 15.61. for those keeping track at home, that’s about a 2% increase per year. not for&amp;nbsp;us!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;you’ll notice i didn’t say &amp;#8220;being green”, tho, that’s a nice side effect, it certainly wasn’t the driving reason. it’s funny how many people think we did it because we’re crazy californian hippies. makes me laugh. no, it has nothing to do with that at all. i mean, have you looked at your power bill&amp;nbsp;lately?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;joc did tons and tons of research prior to the install and we ended up choosing marie phillip at herca solar here in san diego (&lt;a href="http://www.hercasolar.com"&gt;http://www.hercasolar.com&lt;/a&gt;) – they were awesome and are highly recommended by us to anyone interested. just tell them joc and i sent&amp;nbsp;you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;so, to recap: our monthly power budget at worst (until the loan is paid off) is a little less than before the panels, we added a ton of equity to the house and we’ve insulated ourselves from future power rate increases. win, win and&amp;nbsp;win.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;hell, all we need now is an electric car and we’ll be the hippies with the $15 power bill to your $200 one and our $0.00 a month fuel bill to your $200 one.
tho, i suppose at least you won’t be called a&amp;nbsp;hippy.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Topher Chapman</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2011 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>tag:,2011-05-10:blog/2011/May/10/solar-questions/</guid></item><item><title>The Case for Both Symmetrical and Asymmetrical Relationships</title><link>/blog/2009/Apr/06/symmetrical-and-asymmetrical-relationships/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;sorry i’m so late with this.  i know i &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/m3mnoch/status/1426944801"&gt;threatened to write it up&lt;/a&gt; last week, but, you know.  spare time being what it&amp;nbsp;is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;there are quite a few [smart folks[(http://andrewchenblog.com/2009/03/16/friends-versus-followers-twitters-elegant-design-for-grouping-contacts/) out there &lt;a href="http://bokardo.com/archives/relationship-symmetry-in-social-networks-why-facebook-will-go-fully-asymmetric/"&gt;putting forth theories&lt;/a&gt; on why followers (vs. friends) are the “right” way to go.  it’s good stuff.  you should read it as a preface to this.  it’s the kind of stuff i churn over all the time as chief web dude over at &lt;a href="http://www.metaplace.com/"&gt;metaplace&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the crux of the discussion is what’s better? friends or followers?  friends where, through granted requests, you explicitly create a two-way relationship with someone or followers where, by you “following” them back, you create an implicit two-way&amp;nbsp;relationship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and here’s my official thought, social media sites. (twitter, friendfeed, facebook, myspace, etc.)  so listen up — you need&amp;nbsp;both.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;here’s why: both methods, regardless of how they are implemented, are dual&amp;nbsp;purpose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;purpose 1
you create an important relationship between you and another person.  you want to know what they’re doing.  you want to keep in touch.  it’s someone you care about.  you know — that whole “social”&amp;nbsp;thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;purpose 2
it’s a scoreboard, man.  who has the most friends?  who’s the most popular?  who has the biggest network of contacts?  you know — a social&amp;nbsp;leaderboard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“so?” you&amp;nbsp;say.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;well.  it leads to a problem.  mostly, it’s all about the extra&amp;nbsp;noise. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;someone requests a friendship with you, either by clicking “add friend” or simply by following you, and you say “oh, i casually know that person” or “that was nice of them to follow me” and you confirm the&amp;nbsp;relationship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;pretty soon, you have hundreds — even thousands in some cases depending on your notoriety — of&amp;nbsp;friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;well, as it turns out, &lt;a href="http://www.insidefacebook.com/2009/02/27/facebooks-in-house-sociologist-shares-stats-on-users-social-behavior/"&gt;that dunbar number isn’t really a lie&lt;/a&gt; despite facebook’s best efforts.  you don’t really care intimately about all of those people.  but, there you are, with a huge polluted friends list that you can’t really trim down without looking like a huge douche.  (celebrities are mostly exempted from the “trim means douche” rule just because of the sheer number of fans they&amp;nbsp;have)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;you start dropping all those people you knew back in high school or your friend’s parents or whatever from your public friends list, you’re gonna get called on it.  just ask &lt;a href="http://twitter.com/kevinrose"&gt;kevin rose&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;this is a lot of words to really explain something pretty simple: we need to use something akin to the rss&amp;nbsp;model.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;you have private&amp;nbsp;friends.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and you have public&amp;nbsp;subscribers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;this still gives you a public scoreboard number that you can show off like a freakin’ &lt;a href="http://www.cre8d-design.com/2006/03/subscriber-counts-the-new-hit-counter/"&gt;badge of honor&lt;/a&gt; and yet, you still can have a smaller, more manageable list of “important people” that you care&amp;nbsp;about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;subscriber is easy and carefree.  very asymmetrical.  like twitter’s followers.  you subscribe.  they subscribe.  everyone subscribes!  it’s free love and big points for all my friends!  … er… followers.  er…&amp;nbsp;subscribers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;friends, however, is an explicit declaration by both people to “become friends” or promote the simple subscriber relationship to a full-on “lemme know &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ALL&lt;/span&gt; your dirt” relationship.  nobody outside of you two has to know about the relationship.  it can stay clean and&amp;nbsp;pure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;best of all, it gives you a chance to filter the data accordingly. (this is where i pwn all you who are saying to yourselves “why not just use followers and groups, noob!”)  the data you care about is going to be different from friend to subscriber.  you have two different buckets where data pours&amp;nbsp;into.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;let us use facebook as an&amp;nbsp;example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;raise your hand if you hate, hate, hate getting all the retarded app requests from every single person on facebook that you’ve friended.  &lt;em&gt;scans the room and sees everyone but crazy aunt hilda in the back has their hand&amp;nbsp;raised&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;if you merely subscribe to someone, you wouldn’t get those.  you’d get explicit updates (comments, photos, direct messages, etc.) they put out, but not all of the app spam we all&amp;nbsp;“love.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;all that goes into a subscriber bucket (prolly more like a lake, really) that you can dip your toes into and pull out memes or themes every now and then or just submerge yourself and let the noise of it all just wash over&amp;nbsp;you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;however, your newly minted m3mnoch-proposed friends would be sending you full feeds of everything like normal.  all the subscriber stuff, plus app notes or anything else that they’re doing that would implicitly be interesting to you.  because, if they’re one of the 10 or 20 friends you actively follow and they update their facebook bowling app (is there really one?) with the turkey they just threw, dude — you wanna know!  cause you’re prolly playing the same game!  right now!  (i promise i won’t&amp;nbsp;tell…)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;…especially if that saves them the email they’d have to send to you bragging about it&amp;nbsp;anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and then!  then, you don’t have to worry about spammy updates!  the people who you are real friends with would now only include the people you’re prolly on im with all day&amp;nbsp;anyway.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and once you can get the wires that tight, there’s all kinds of cool integration you can do.  automatic trust-type stuff you just can’t assume with today’s friending setups.  not to mention awesome data mining and discovery stuff you can assemble from a developer’s&amp;nbsp;standpoint.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;hell.  you might even be able to pull all that external im conversation onto your&amp;nbsp;site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i mean, wouldn’t it be nice to not have to worry about how many people billy sends an app request to because you would know that all his friends — not subscribers — are honest-to-god interested in&amp;nbsp;it?&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Topher Chapman</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 06 Apr 2009 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>tag:,2009-04-06:blog/2009/Apr/06/symmetrical-and-asymmetrical-relationships/</guid></item><item><title>Web-based MMOG Imagineering</title><link>/blog/2007/Jan/31/web-based-mmo-imagineering/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;i’ve been doing a lot of imagineering (man, i love that word) lately when it comes to web-based mmogs. lots of stuff running the gamut from super-secret ideas i can’t tell anyone about right now to general wonderings and&amp;nbsp;observations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;well. i think i’ll just dump some of them out right here so i have them collected&amp;nbsp;somewhere.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;subscription fees are choice&amp;nbsp;inhibiting.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;paying those subscription fees certainly add up. i know you can say “well, just pay them for the 3 months you play and then get rid of&amp;nbsp;them.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;no. it doesn’t work like&amp;nbsp;that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the thing with a subscription fee is that it represents commitment. there’s a high switching cost involved. and, since not very many people can afford to pay subscriptions for, oh, 15 games over the course of two years, you tend not to move on to those newer games. we basically have the wow effect where everyone is really only in a few&amp;nbsp;games.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it really moves buying games into parallel with buying cars. you really like different models and styles, but, you have to make an informed decision about one — and only one — you’ll enjoy and use enough to make its acquisition worth&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;with non-subscription games, they are more like traditional media. more like movies or music. you just pop it in and play it whenever you want. you know that from purchase so there is no “will i use this in the future?” or “will i like this better than everquest?” or “will something better come along?”  the only factor is the “now” factor. how does buying it impact you right&amp;nbsp;now?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;non-subscription games are very much more pickup-putdown with no real switching cost. that lets you consume more game&amp;nbsp;media.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;web servers are more conducive to a persistent online&amp;nbsp;world.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;this one is tricky and i’m not going to try not to get too awful web-geeky on&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the gist is that, for example, myspace.com has millions of concurrent users — all of whom can be on the exact same page at the exact same time. that is absolutely no different performance-wise than all of those million people being on a million separate&amp;nbsp;pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;not only performance, but the web is better at information dissemination than a graphical, high-visual&amp;nbsp;client.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for example, if these million players were all in one place on a wow server (assuming of course the server wouldn’t go chernobyl on the situation) you wouldn’t really be able to pick out any one particular player to attack or inspect or what-have-you. with something like the singular, you can just ask them how many users per page you want to&amp;nbsp;see?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i mean, has anyone ever seen how many google results come up for the word&amp;nbsp;“page?”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;oh sure, you say, but there’s an immersive, graphical richness that can’t be achieved with this silly text and lightweight graphical environment called the web. to that, i say, use the best-of-breed parts of both. use the data layout of a web page and the graphically rich aspects of flash for your deeper spatial relation&amp;nbsp;needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the future of mmogs is going to be about ajax-enabled rest&amp;nbsp;applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;event-based feedback consumable in sub-5 minute&amp;nbsp;increments.&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;as you may know, signing on and logging into wow may take you a while. hell, it takes 5 minutes on a good day to get logged into something you can actually&amp;nbsp;“play.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;contrast that with 3 or 4 seconds to get to a play screen with travian. your login credentials are cached so all you really need is a bookmark to your village&amp;nbsp;overview.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;now, with that same 5 minutes you’re logging into wow, i can check guild messages, send appropriate reinforcements, build a new building, train some additional troops and send out a spy mission — and still have time left&amp;nbsp;over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;that’s a lot of gameplay compacted into a short amount of&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and, that’s the kind of stuff you just can’t do in a 3d&amp;nbsp;world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;by the time you wander over to the auction house, i’ve already hit the marketplace, scanned the available trades, accepted a trade, sent merchants and moved on to planning my next action. and that’s only if you happen to be close to the auction house when we&amp;nbsp;start.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;now that we’ve decided that gameplay interaction is faster with a web-based mmog, what can we do with&amp;nbsp;it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;well. what makes gameplay addictive? incremental goals and achieving them, right? well. now, we can have more. more incremental goals and they can be closer together. it’s called instant gratification and it’s a goddamn&amp;nbsp;drug.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and, what quality makes a game permeate throughout your life? being able to get in and get out of the world instantly. how easy is it to check your inbox for new messages? how easy is it to check the box score of the game last night? how easy is it to check what google’s stock closed at today? how easy is it to see if your reinforcements got attacked in your&amp;nbsp;alliance?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;answer: super-easy. mere seconds&amp;nbsp;even.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;that turns playing a game into a “walk-by” experience. busy working around the house? on an excel document? writing an email? tv&amp;nbsp;commercialing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;multi-task gaming. pop-in. pop-out. top of&amp;nbsp;mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and, we haven’t even touched the portability aspect.  connected to the same game on your treo 650?  yep, you sure&amp;nbsp;are.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the web is the single most efficient content distribution channel in history.  mmogs, at their core, are just specialized, interactive content distribution in need of a super-efficient&amp;nbsp;channel.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Topher Chapman</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 31 Jan 2007 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>tag:,2007-01-31:blog/2007/Jan/31/web-based-mmo-imagineering/</guid></item><item><title>Menopause FTW!</title><link>/blog/2006/Dec/11/menopause-ftw/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;if you haven’t played bookworm adventures yet, you’re missing out. something fierce. it’s completely cool to beat down badguys with words like “bodacious” or with a gemmed-up&amp;nbsp;“aviary.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;my favorite tho? smacking an enemy who is overly susceptible to color words with my hammer that does extra damage on metal words with&amp;nbsp;“bronze.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;hell.&amp;nbsp;yeah.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and, yes. i’ve even seen the rare diamond tile — holy badass,&amp;nbsp;batman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;you &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MUST&lt;/span&gt; play this game. riddling sphinxes. raging boss battles. snappy dialog. is absolutely necessitates your&amp;nbsp;attention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;especially when you one-hit a 29-heart badguy with “temperatures” and a fistful of&amp;nbsp;gems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;UPDATE&lt;/span&gt;: ha!  i just found this: &lt;a href="http://www.rtsoft.com/pages/dscroll.php"&gt;dungeon scroll&lt;/a&gt;.   it looks like bookworm adventures is a total and complete ripoff.  funny.  i’ll check out dungeon scroll and see how it&amp;nbsp;plays.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Topher Chapman</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 11 Dec 2006 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>tag:,2006-12-11:blog/2006/Dec/11/menopause-ftw/</guid></item><item><title>MarbleBlast Ultra: Like Warm Butter</title><link>/blog/2006/Mar/01/marble-blast-ultra/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;so. i’d been avoiding it since i downloaded the demo and devoured the half a dozen or so levels that ship with&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i bought marbleblast ultra and it’s a&amp;nbsp;riot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the controls are super responsive, but have enough play in them that is just ‘feels right.’ it reminds me a lot of when mario 64 first came out. simply maneuvering mario around that world was most of the fun of the&amp;nbsp;game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it has that gentle balance between inertia and weight that is so much fun in driving games when you swing the ass-end of your porsche around a tight corner as you power-slide through the&amp;nbsp;curve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;yeah. it’s like&amp;nbsp;that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i powered through both the entire set of beginner levels and the intermediate levels, making par times or better on all of them. that’s 40 straight levels of love, folks. all of it good. (a few of them, i was even ranked in the top 1000 — woot!) and, i still have the whole set of 20 advanced levels to&amp;nbsp;go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;then, i fired up the multiplayer mode for a bit of ball-on-ball action. it’s a total kick in the&amp;nbsp;pants.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where the single player levels are more like precision highwire acts, the multiplayer levels are more like a skatepark-come-moshpit. you roll around, bouncing off of each other as you chase ‘gems’ around the ‘park’ for points. the one with the most points in the time limit&amp;nbsp;wins.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;you’ll find yourself bounce-blasting off ridges and screeching around corners in a balls-out (pun intended) race to the next grouping of&amp;nbsp;gems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i can see why the guys at penny-arcade love&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;speaking of multiplayer, tho, there’s something incredible that needs to be pointed out. i’ve seen a couple of articles on how xbox live and achievements are bringing back the old arcade ‘high score’ love from decades&amp;nbsp;past.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;this is&amp;nbsp;different.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;instead of one monolithic score (you have one of those too) times and scores and rankings are broken out by level. so, basically, it comes down to who performed best in that 2 minutes of gameplay — one level at a&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it’s leaderboards for each individual level. between you and your friends (or those top-page crazies who complete a level in 3.5 seconds that takes me 1:30? how? email me with how!), who can complete the level faster. there were several instances where i’d completed a level under par, but went back just to dust my buddy trizity’s times. heh. talk about&amp;nbsp;replayability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;when did casual games get so&amp;nbsp;competitive?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it raises the bar and redefines multiplayer gaming in a casual game setting. simply a fantastic game burrowing down to the very essence that is&amp;nbsp;‘gaming.’&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Topher Chapman</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2006 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>tag:,2006-03-01:blog/2006/Mar/01/marble-blast-ultra/</guid></item><item><title>Reporting vs. Blogging on Games: A Half-Assed Manifesto</title><link>/blog/2006/Feb/15/reporting-vs-blogging-on-games/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;this fake war is happening right now between game ‘journalists’ and game ‘bloggers.’ lemme&amp;nbsp;explain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i don’t really read much of gamespot, ign etc. anymore. i like reading the bloggers who write about games for a more honest, unbeholden-to-sponsors opinion. if i wanted paraphrased marketing spin, i’d just read the actual press&amp;nbsp;releases.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;that’s not to say those sites or magazines don’t have original content. they really do. a lot of the time, it’s even almost interesting. sort of in the only way those sites can be interesting. top 10 lists or game reviews. the narrow space where they can be critical of a game — by comparing them to other games. any mention of a company or any specific developers, tho, is always watered down. ‘this could be my opinion or that could be. objective journalism doesn’t let me pick tho. you have to&amp;nbsp;guess!’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;heh. even game reviews only float between 6.0 and 9.5. what’s the point of having 3’s or 4’s or 5’s if you never use them? shouldn’t 5 be average? according to a bell curve, shouldn’t the bulk of games be 5’s? personally, my rating system consists of one of three options: good games. mediocre games. and bad games. good, bad or indifferent. that’s the correct order of the&amp;nbsp;universe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;but, i&amp;nbsp;digress.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;the problem is that traditional journalism is about unbiased facts. video game journalism is, however, subjective. therefore, not even technically&amp;nbsp;journalism.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i want opinion. i want to be part of the meta-conversation about games. i don’t just want to consume industry marketing messaging. i want critical thinking done by these guys. i don’t want their half-assed attempt at portraying ‘the other&amp;nbsp;side.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i don’t think anyone like gamespot (i hate to pick on them in particular. feel free to insert your favorite ‘news’ site instead.) can really call sony out for being stupid. why would sony give them marketing co-op money in exchange for calling them dumb? what you end up with is a lot of tied-hands and flat, uninteresting&amp;nbsp;‘reporting.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;that’s where this whole ‘new games journalism’ crap comes&amp;nbsp;in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;heh. in case you couldn’t tell by my tone, i don’t really buy into the pretentious nonsense that is ‘ngj.’ it’s not about who can wax most esoteric regarding the minutiae of this love we call ‘interactive&amp;nbsp;entertainment.’&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;no. just tell us what you thought. give us an honest opinion. that’s really all we want. if a game is crap, let us know. if it is simply average — despite it’s heritage — call it out. bring pain down upon those who dare to destroy our beloved icons! be interesting, not effusive. we don’t want to read poetry about some shitty game,&amp;nbsp;man.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in other words, do what bloggers&amp;nbsp;do.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we’re slanted. we’re opinionated. we’re jaded. that’s the beauty of it. collectively, all of the blogging voices make up a fairly balanced&amp;nbsp;opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;no. seriously. hear me&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;for every blogger that loves some particular game or style of game, there’s another one who despises it. both are equally loud. both froth and spit bile about the opposing side. (well. the interesting ones anyway. the passionate ones.) if you are interested in balanced opinions, as a reader, you can review both opinions and make your own decision. the difference is that instead of a single writer trying to whitewash both sides in a single article. you have two blazing icons shouting the merits of their independent, even more diametrically opposed opinions. we’re loud and proud,&amp;nbsp;baby.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;the best part about video game bloggers? find someone you agree with and play what he plays. if your preferred flavors of games are entirely alike, then, they’ll never steer you&amp;nbsp;wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;traditional game journalism, however, can’t do that. somebody out there thinks metal gear solid is a good game. i sure as hell don’t. holy boring, batman. if i wanted to watch a stealth/intrigue movie, i’d rent one. last time i checked, i was trying to play a game. not trying to figure out how to skip&amp;nbsp;cutscenes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i can say mgs sucked. traditional game journos can’t. because, for some gamers who are into that, well, it was a great&amp;nbsp;game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;how do you rate&amp;nbsp;that?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;how do you give a concrete value to a subjective medium that will be equally applied to all your readers’ varied interests? that’s why movie reviewers are individual reviewers. the review is their opinion — not the magazine’s opinion. as an organization, the magazine is responsible for assessing games for someone who likes rts and someone who hates them. me? i think they are work, not fun. if the magazine says total annihilation is a 9.0 out of 10, does that mean i’ll like it? hell&amp;nbsp;no.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;movies are a similar thing. find a reviewer who tends to agree with you and go with it. who the hell cares what roeper (talk about an arrogant prick…. wow.) thinks when you always agree with ebert. (he is the absolute best movie reviewer of our&amp;nbsp;time.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;you can do that with bloggers. they represent no one but themselves. bloggers are beholden, not to the conflict-of-interest inspiring advertisers on their site, but to their own integrity and pride of&amp;nbsp;workmanship.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;what am i saying? i guess i have no&amp;nbsp;idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;something along the lines of look to traditional game journalism for regurgitation. new game journalism for pretension. independent bloggers for honest&amp;nbsp;opinion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;video game journalism is about opinion&amp;nbsp;dammit!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i mean, c’mon! can’t we all just get&amp;nbsp;along?&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Topher Chapman</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2006 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>tag:,2006-02-15:blog/2006/Feb/15/reporting-vs-blogging-on-games/</guid></item><item><title>Game Design Brief: Warbinder</title><link>/blog/2006/Feb/10/game-design-brief-warbinder/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;INTRODUCTION&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Binders are greater lords who bind together teams of warriors, train them, and then enter them into deadly combat with other Binders’ teams to fight for the ultimate title of Warbinder. Will you be the next&amp;nbsp;Warbinder?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DESCRIPTION&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You start as a fledgling Binder with only 8 lowly warriors under your control. Each individual Bound has a multitude of differing strengths and abilities. From here, you have a few options for building a well integrated team of mighty gladiators whose skills supplement and balance each&amp;nbsp;other.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CAPTURE&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can get out and scour the world capturing, bribing or persuading fighters to join your cause. The method of capture you should choose will depend on the nature of the particular Bound you are trying to bring under your control. Some are more aggressive. Some are more&amp;nbsp;crafty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;TRADE&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Logging into the secure web site or through the game interface will allow Binders to connect and trade Bound with other Binders. Since the warriors have fixed cost values and variable training levels, the trade combinations are limitless. Perhaps you have trained your lowly Umglot to an amazing level, but he doesn’t fit well into the firearms team you are building. Trade him for a vastly more powerful, but not as well trained Nitarian Flame&amp;nbsp;Sniper.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;PURCHASE&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through secure online transactions, you can purchase groups of warriors outright. These “booster packs” will include a variety of untrained Bound based on rarity and point&amp;nbsp;values.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you have built up your force, train your warriors well for soon it will be time to enter the coliseum for your first training battle. Carefully command your Bound during series after series of single player action against Binder configurable training Bots. Use the Bot control panel to tune the Bot’s combat abilities anywhere from a particular fighting style to general melee and train your Bound how to defeat them. Teach them combat formations and individual skills to counter any foe. The more you train, the better your Bound will be in live&amp;nbsp;combat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, log in, find a worthy adversary and put it all on the line for the title of&amp;nbsp;Warbinder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The huge metal doors hum and then slam shut behind your team of 5 well trained Bound. O’Keefe is your wolfman bristling with electro-static knives. Shahara begins to glow with armor made of light as she begins to cast a protection spell. Kongar, a monstrous barbarian, steps forward with his dual, humming battle axes. H’rathsis hovers near by as he readies the stinging spikes along his manta ray shaped body. And finally, Jake steps forward and racks his over and under double-barreled shotgun. He clenches his teeth, puts on his shades and says grimly, “Let’s get it&amp;nbsp;on.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On the far side, as your opponents enter the ring, you offer up a prayer that you have taught your team enough about teamwork – that you have taught them enough about each other – that you have taught them enough about themselves to not only come out alive, but to win. And then, someday, that they will make you a&amp;nbsp;Warbinder.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GENRE&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game takes place in a world of techno-sorcery. Sweeping, flaming swords carve through concrete walls and mighty sorcerers battle against armored troops carrying shock rifles. Search far and wide for your future Bound. Trek through rolling hillsides and forests, in over populated hi-tech megacities or hike the deserts and canyons of the world of Galtaar. Home of the most powerful beings in the cosmos –&amp;nbsp;Warbinders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;KEY&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FEATURES&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;100 different races and styles of warriors with different&amp;nbsp;abilities.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Build complimentary teams based around strategic combinations of individual&amp;nbsp;powers.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Train your Bound to a higher skill level to become more&amp;nbsp;powerful.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Advanced learning &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AI&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Many different skills for characters to&amp;nbsp;learn.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Shift characters around to build different&amp;nbsp;teams.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find, purchase or trade to acquire different&amp;nbsp;characters.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Trade characters in the game environment or on the web&amp;nbsp;site.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Research, inspect and arrange your team in game, on the web site or even on your &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDA&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Topher Chapman</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 10 Feb 2006 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>tag:,2006-02-10:blog/2006/Feb/10/game-design-brief-warbinder/</guid></item><item><title>Ideas are a Dime a Dozen</title><link>/blog/2006/Feb/07/ideas-are-a-dime-a-dozen/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;i thought i would share a piece i wrote about a million years ago — okay. actually only 5. i was feeling a bit melancholy after having written a pretty decent game design brief, shipped it off to bioware, had it swapped to lucas arts (in exchange for kotor) where it eventually became the xbox game&amp;nbsp;“gladius.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;heh. with not even so much as a &lt;em&gt;pat&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;pat&lt;/em&gt; “nice&amp;nbsp;work.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;man, i wish i had taken some screenshots of their ‘back of the box’ bullets when they first announced the title.  70% of them were god damn verbatim.  ah well. at least i know i can play at that level,&amp;nbsp;eh?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Game development ideas are everywhere. Everyone has one. How many times have you and your friends been sitting around thinking to yourselves “Wouldn’t it be great if someone made this into a video game?” What if there was somewhere where you could put your ideas and have game developers actually take them under&amp;nbsp;advisement?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This, of course, only works if two things happen. First, you have to be willing to share your “million dollar idea” and, second, game developers have to implement&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hate to be the one to break this to you, but, that idea of yours may be original and unique and the best thing since sliced bread, but there isn’t a game developer in the world who will sign an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NDA&lt;/span&gt; to listen to your idea. They get hundreds upon hundreds of “idea” submissions every day. Not to mention the ideas of their own. You have to build it yourself or it won’t get made. That is, unless you push it out there to the game development community at large and hope someone picks it&amp;nbsp;up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, if you can cover that part, we at Addicting Entertainment are hoping to cover the sharing of our collective ideas with the people actually building games. If your idea is clever enough to make it into a game, you finally get to actually experience your&amp;nbsp;idea.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here’s where you may want to just stop reading and opt out of any idea sharing:
We’re not in this to make money. Any ideas posted here are fair&amp;nbsp;game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By posting your “million dollar idea” you are turning it into a “zero dollar idea.” If some developer takes a fancy to your killer new idea for an &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FPS&lt;/span&gt; weapon, well, it sucks to be you. — In the monetary sense. You, of course, still retain the bragging rights to say “Dude! I posted my idea and id made it real! Woot!” You aren’t going to get paid for it. Not by us, nor (probably) by the game developer. Although, it would be nice if they publicly gave you a slap-on-the-back-you-rock-thanks. But they are not obligated to at&amp;nbsp;all.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You might be asking, “Well, dammit. Why the hell would I post my great idea then?” Our answer? Because you are a gamer. We all are. If you are in game development or thinking about being in game development for the money, you need to rethink your career. Sure, just like in the music business there are a few rockstars (pun intended) but also, like in the music business, the majority of us slave away at our labor of love for free or barely enough to eat. If you want to make money building software, move into enterprise level software development. Boring, but lucrative. Games are fun, but you’ll likely be piss-poor if you do it for a&amp;nbsp;living.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So you might as well share with the community and advance the art and science of&amp;nbsp;gaming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;here’s what i was thinking. i’ll make an open call for user submitted design documents. i’ll post a design brief in a bit as an example. i’ve set up a category for them. i’ll see if i can get a couple up there that i’ve got rolling around in my head. there’s just not enough time for me to make them all, so i might as well put them up here just in case someone else wants to build one or&amp;nbsp;two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;not sure how many i’ll see, but it would be fun to find&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Topher Chapman</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 07 Feb 2006 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>tag:,2006-02-07:blog/2006/Feb/07/ideas-are-a-dime-a-dozen/</guid></item><item><title>Damn my Obsessiveness</title><link>/blog/2006/Jan/26/fastr/</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Water! Temple! Bug!&amp;nbsp;Woot!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Pulse Pounding. Head Swimming. Fingers flying manically across my keyboard. Scratching and scribbling noisily, struggling to find just the right&amp;nbsp;word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Damn this tiny tablet keyboard! My long, gangly fingers mis-stepping the entire way. I feel like I spend more time on the backspace key than actually poking at letters. Argh! Too&amp;nbsp;late.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sunshine. I need to go&amp;nbsp;faster.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No! I need to concentrate on the next&amp;nbsp;word.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dinosaur! Got it! 10 points! I’m a&amp;nbsp;genius!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catching up to Seraphim now. It won’t be long before I claim that coveted top spot. Before I can reap the glory and spread the fear. Behold the giant:&amp;nbsp;m3mnoch!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Um. How the hell do you spell “exuberant?” Wait! No one is going to use that as a tag. That’s the dumbest thing I’ve ever&amp;nbsp;thought.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teeth. Simile…. Ack. &lt;em&gt;click&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;click&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;click&lt;/em&gt; I meant Smile. No? Clown? 4&amp;nbsp;Points!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ranking is falling. There is only 46 seconds left in the round. I’ve fallen to 23rd. I don’t know if I can&amp;nbsp;recover.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think, dammit! Simple words. Descriptive&amp;nbsp;words.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fraudulent. What? Fraudulent? Where on earth did I come up with that one? Better yet, who in their right mind would tag a photo as “fraudulent?” And, how on earth did I spell that right the first time?  What?  Next photo already?
Sand! Yes! 8 points. Hanging steady at 23rd. Times almost&amp;nbsp;up!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Erg. I have no idea on this one. 3… Banging out letters. 2… No! Not yet! 1… I can get&amp;nbsp;it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Too&amp;nbsp;Late.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What? “&lt;span class="caps"&gt;THE&lt;/span&gt; Kevin Federline check out my site yo!” beat me? The absolute shame. I lost out in a competition of cognitive prowess to Kevin Federline? I guess there’s no chance Britney will shack up with me now,&amp;nbsp;eh?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is it really 9:30 already? Have I really been doing this for an hour? Wow. I need to pull up out of this swirling vacuum&amp;nbsp;of….&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vacuum! I bet that was the last&amp;nbsp;one!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Oops. New round. Gotta&amp;nbsp;hurry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Puppy? Paw? Fur! Yes! 7&amp;nbsp;points!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Huh? What? What was the link? Oh, yeah. it’s &lt;a href="http://randomchaos.com/games/fastr/"&gt;http://randomchaos.com/games/fastr/&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Topher Chapman</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2006 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate><guid>tag:,2006-01-26:blog/2006/Jan/26/fastr/</guid></item><item><title>Fixing Game Economies</title><link>/blog/2005/Oct/29/fixing-game-economies/</link><description>&lt;h2&gt;The Hero&amp;#8217;s Journey and Wage&amp;nbsp;Slaves&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the real world not everyone can be a winner.  Not everyone is successful.  I know it&amp;#8217;s hard to believe, but there actually are people out there who don&amp;#8217;t like their job.  The way real world economies are built depends on a lower wage class &amp;#8212; the wage slave.  There has to be someone to work the low paying, thankless jobs from the garbage men to the guy at the counter at McDonald&amp;#8217;s.  Not everyone can make absurd amounts of money just by essentially &amp;#8216;showing up and having fun.&amp;#8217;  If that happened, our economy would come crashing to its knees.  Inflation would rise uncontrollably until the dollar approached near&amp;nbsp;worthlessness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It would be just plain&amp;nbsp;bad.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Game worlds don&amp;#8217;t work like that though.  In a video game, everyone can be a winner.  In a video game, players want to have fun and win.  They have that right.  After all, they bought and paid for the game.  Why should anyone be expected to play a game where they are just one of the unwashed masses teeming with&amp;nbsp;mediocrity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike in the real world they don&amp;#8217;t have to battle each other to be the best.  They battle the environment and the monstrous inhabitants living there.  Each individual player is on their own Hero&amp;#8217;s Journey.  They all are playing to become more wealthy and powerful and none of that really depends on the other players in the game.  It might in some small way, but, by and large, games are built to allow a single player to succeed without the help of anyone&amp;nbsp;else.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Along each step of this journey, as they gain more experience and get more powerful, they are able to accumulate wealth easier.  This propagates economic models that show each player&amp;#8217;s individual wealth and power grow on an exponential curve.  Goods and services provided in the game don&amp;#8217;t.  And they shouldn&amp;#8217;t.  If prices went up for these goods and services, lower level players wouldn&amp;#8217;t be able to afford them.  They wouldn&amp;#8217;t have any fun and the game would tank.  This causes inflation within the game.  More money, fewer products for you to spend it&amp;nbsp;on.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Money Sinks Aren&amp;#8217;t&amp;nbsp;Working&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To counter this exponential growth in wealth across the board, developers have tried to implement money sinks.  They are trying to siphon money out of the system with things like paying for transportation or paying rent on any property the player&amp;#8217;s character might own.  The issue with this is that the sinks aren&amp;#8217;t exponential and thus won&amp;#8217;t match the character&amp;#8217;s potential income.  The growth in wealth will always outpace the cost applied to these sinks.  Eventually, they will get to a point where the player is making so much money in the game that these flatly priced money sinks will essentially have no effect on their wallets and we&amp;#8217;re back to the same&amp;nbsp;problem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The developers could scale the cost of these sinks up, but that&amp;#8217;s silly.  Just because my character is a higher level than yours, I have to pay a higher price for my equipment?  Even though it&amp;#8217;s the very same equipment you are purchasing?  Shouldn&amp;#8217;t that be the other way around?  With money comes power and influence &amp;#8212; price discounts, not increases.  Regardless, not only are there metagaming ways around this weird price fixing (low level fences, for example) but, it&amp;#8217;s just a terrible idea.  How many players do you know that enjoy paying arbitrary &amp;#8216;taxes&amp;#8217; in any game they&amp;nbsp;play?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Why Do We Have Two&amp;nbsp;Currencies?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The problem at the root of all this is the simple fact that a game has two currencies &amp;#8212; experience points and money.  really, these days, we have to have three currencies.  two we earn and one we purchase with real&amp;nbsp;money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sure the theory sounds like a greatgood idea, after all, you need more money to purchase better equipment so it should just balance out.  But, the player doesn&amp;#8217;t need every suit of armor or sword they come upon.  Either their character can&amp;#8217;t use it or it&amp;#8217;s not as good as their current item so they sell&amp;nbsp;them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, you can kill 100 different monsters with a 10gp sword, but the items and equipment and money that come off of those 100 monsters are more than likely worth a lot more than the 20gp upgraded sword.  That, and along the way you are getting experience points for killing the monsters.  So, that 10gp sword gets more effective without anymore cost to the&amp;nbsp;player.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our example, it costs the player nothing to make fistfuls of gold and become more powerful.  That 10gp sword is netting huge &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ROI&lt;/span&gt; because of the multiplying effect of having these two currencies.  All this and it&amp;#8217;s actually&amp;nbsp;fun!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Money Equals&amp;nbsp;Power&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The simple solution is to tie money to power.  If experience points were inextricably linked to gold, it would negate the desire to stockpile the money and reduce us back down to a single currency.  If characters had to pay 1 gold (or however your currency breaks down) for each experience point, it would solve the problem.  You need to pay for&amp;nbsp;power.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will make money scarce again.  Does the player buy that new armor upgrade or do they put the money (in addition to experience points) into leveling up?  What&amp;#8217;s the best part about that money spent on leveling up?  They aren&amp;#8217;t buying anything they can resell and the gold required scales with power.  It essentially drops us back down to a single&amp;nbsp;currency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This levels the playing field.  Just because a character is a higher level doesn&amp;#8217;t necessarily mean he can afford goods and services any easier than a lower level character.  Sure, it&amp;#8217;s easier for him to make and hold money, but players should be able to make that decision.  Do you think they will want to hold the money and stagnate in their power or do you think they will spend that money on experience points and be broke&amp;nbsp;again?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The idea of paying for training is essentially what we are talking about here.  It&amp;#8217;s an ages old concept in games &amp;#8212; one that was done away with in this age of instant gratification.  As it turns out, paying for training is actually a critical part of keeping the economy in check.  It gives those players somewhere to spend their&amp;nbsp;money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buy better equipment or advance in levels?  It&amp;#8217;s a fantastic choice to put to the player.  Chances are that the entire game is built around choices like that anyway.  Do you want the fireball spell or the strength buff spell?  More mana or more hit points?  This means it shouldn&amp;#8217;t affect gameplay in any negative&amp;nbsp;fashion. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, it should actually enhance the gameplay by adding an additional strategic element to&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Topher Chapman</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2005 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate><guid>tag:,2005-10-29:blog/2005/Oct/29/fixing-game-economies/</guid></item></channel></rss>