<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Topher Chapman</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.topherchapman.com/feeds/writing.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2016-02-29T00:00:00-08:00</updated><entry><title>FanFic Fight Scene</title><link href="/blog/2016/Feb/29/fanfic-fight-ff/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-02-29T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Topher Chapman</name></author><id>tag:,2016-02-29:blog/2016/Feb/29/fanfic-fight-ff/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;sort of like the summary above alludes to, i relished this opportunity to address a terrible grievance cast upon the world.  this one, right&amp;nbsp;here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PsZ-acZYqco]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;in the first 30 seconds of that video, something so very wrong gets spoken, that it made me literally cry out and stomp my feet in&amp;nbsp;outrage.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;there is no goddamn way drogo would beat conan in a&amp;nbsp;fight.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;take, for example, the most relevant detail:  drogo lives in a gritty, realistic world.  conan lives in over-the-top crazy town.  ffs, conan snapped the neck of a bull when he was a teenager!  with his bare&amp;nbsp;hands!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(note, i&amp;#8217;m talking about &lt;em&gt;literary&lt;/em&gt; conan here, not &lt;em&gt;ah-nahld&lt;/em&gt;&amp;nbsp;conan)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;it&amp;#8217;s like saying, who would win in a fight &amp;#8212; wolverine or mike tyson in his prime?&amp;nbsp;duh.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;anyway, &lt;a href="http://fantasy-faction.com/forum/(feb-2016)-fanfic/(feb-2016)-fanfic-submission-thread/msg134396/#msg134396"&gt;my entry&lt;/a&gt; this month explores the&amp;nbsp;topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i&amp;#8217;ve recreated it here, for your fancy reading:  &lt;a href="/stories/bulls-and-horses"&gt;Bulls and&amp;nbsp;Horses&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Even More Clarion</title><link href="/blog/2016/Feb/16/second-clarion-story/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-02-16T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Topher Chapman</name></author><id>tag:,2016-02-16:blog/2016/Feb/16/second-clarion-story/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;here we go again!  the second of my entries to that fancy &lt;a href="http://clarion.ucsd.edu/index.html"&gt;clarion workshop&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;thing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;this time, it&amp;#8217;s a short story about some poor woman, broken and suffering after crashing to the ground &amp;#8212; if only she&amp;#8217;d not botched the assassination&amp;nbsp;attempt.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="/stories/stress-fracture"&gt;Stress Fracture&amp;nbsp;Excerpt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Applying to Clarion</title><link href="/blog/2016/Feb/09/clarion-application/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-02-09T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Topher Chapman</name></author><id>tag:,2016-02-09:blog/2016/Feb/09/clarion-application/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;wait &amp;#8212; what is clarion, you ask?  here&amp;#8217;s what they&amp;nbsp;say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clarion is an intensive six-week summer program focused on fundamentals particular to the writing of science fiction and fantasy short stories. It is considered a premier proving and training ground for aspiring writers of science fiction, fantasy, and horror. Instructors are among the most respected writers and editors working in the field today. Over one third of our graduates have been published and many have gone on to critical acclaim. The list of distinguished Clarion alumni includes Ed Bryant, Octavia Butler, Bob Crais, Cory Doctorow, George Alec Effinger, Nalo Hopkinson, James Patrick Kelly, Vonda McIntyre, Kim Stanley Robinson, Martha Soukup, Kelly Link, Bruce Sterling, and many&amp;nbsp;others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;apparently, they only take 18 people each year.  well, here goes&amp;nbsp;nothing&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i&amp;#8217;m working through two of my short stories right now for submission.  in theory, they&amp;#8217;re supposed to represent my best work to&amp;nbsp;date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;you tell me if you think it&amp;nbsp;is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;here&amp;#8217;s the opening scene for a story about guns and dragons (it&amp;#8217;s like peanut butter and chocolate!):  &lt;a href="/stories/hearts-of-fire"&gt;Hearts of Fire&amp;nbsp;Excerpt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Breaking the Fourth Wall</title><link href="/blog/2016/Jan/14/fourth-wall-ff/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-01-14T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Topher Chapman</name></author><id>tag:,2016-01-14:blog/2016/Jan/14/fourth-wall-ff/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;so it turns out this month&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://fantasy-faction.com/forum/(jan-2016)-breaking-the-fourth-wall/(jan-2016)-breaking-the-fourth-wall-submission-thread/msg128612/#msg128612"&gt;fantasy faction contest&lt;/a&gt; was to write a story about breaking the fourth wall.  &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Fourth_wall"&gt;wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; has a pretty good description of just what that means if you&amp;#8217;re&amp;nbsp;not familiar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;long story short (ha!  see what i did there?!?), it&amp;#8217;s a device that works well&amp;nbsp;with comedy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i can totes&amp;nbsp;do funny.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;so, yeah, this month was fun to write.  originally, i was planning on doing a zombie hunter thing &amp;#8212; had a great nugget of an idea that i may revive (see?  funny!) later.  that&amp;#8217;s when i remembered a conversation my d&amp;amp;d guys and i had ages ago.  it involved dragons, so, of course, i wrote about dragons.
finally, here it is:  &lt;a href="/stories/fucking-dragon"&gt;But, I’m a&amp;nbsp;F#@%ing Dragon!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>