<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Topher Chapman</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://www.topherchapman.com/feeds/writing.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2016-02-09T00:00:00-08:00</updated><entry><title>Applying to Clarion</title><link href="/blog/2016/Feb/09/clarion-application/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2016-02-09T00:00:00-08:00</updated><author><name>Topher Chapman</name></author><id>tag:,2016-02-09:blog/2016/Feb/09/clarion-application/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;wait &amp;#8212; what is clarion, you ask?  here&amp;#8217;s what they&amp;nbsp;say:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Clarion is an intensive six-week summer program focused on fundamentals particular to the writing of science fiction and fantasy short stories. It is considered a premier proving and training ground for aspiring writers of science fiction, fantasy, and horror. Instructors are among the most respected writers and editors working in the field today. Over one third of our graduates have been published and many have gone on to critical acclaim. The list of distinguished Clarion alumni includes Ed Bryant, Octavia Butler, Bob Crais, Cory Doctorow, George Alec Effinger, Nalo Hopkinson, James Patrick Kelly, Vonda McIntyre, Kim Stanley Robinson, Martha Soukup, Kelly Link, Bruce Sterling, and many&amp;nbsp;others.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;apparently, they only take 18 people each year.  well, here goes&amp;nbsp;nothing&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;i&amp;#8217;m working through two of my short stories right now for submission.  in theory, they&amp;#8217;re supposed to represent my best work to&amp;nbsp;date.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;you tell me if you think it&amp;nbsp;is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;here&amp;#8217;s the opening scene for a story about guns and dragons (it&amp;#8217;s like peanut butter and chocolate!):  &lt;a href="/stories/hearts-of-fire"&gt;Hearts of Fire&amp;nbsp;Excerpt&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>